Elesandro Bornhofen, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Researcher, QGG - Aarhus University

Ny Munkegade 116, 8000 Aarhus C, Denmark

♠ https://elesandrobornhofen.github.io
☑ bornhofen@qgg.au.dk

https://goo.gl/Fw56WP Last update: 10th July 2021



Career highlights & interests

I have been researching on plant genetics and breeding for over ten years focused on variety development and germplasm enhancement. Over this period, I have lead or involved myself in numerous scientific projects from a variety of areas of expertise. I recently become engaged in projects aiming to explore genotype-by-environment interaction, and multi-omics in genomic selection and prediction of single crosses in grass species. I am constantly learning and acquiring experience on the latest tools with potential applications in plant breeding, which includes: high-throughput phenotyping, spatial statistics for the analyses of field trials, machine-learning, omics-assisted breeding. The potential of bridge classical breeding and state-of-the-art tools to develop better plant varieties that will keep meeting the growing demand is what motivates me. Additional interests include equity investments, behavioral finance, business, and financial markets.

Educational training

2015 – 2019 Ph.D. in Genetics and Plant Breeding

University of São Paulo, "Luiz de Queiroz" College of Agriculture, Piracicaba, São Paulo, Brazil.

Advisor: Ph.D. Natal A. Vello

Thesis: Genetic analysis reveals opportunities and obstacles of tolerance to the Asian soybean rust fungus.

2018 - Ph.D. sandwich at University of Minnesota

Advisor: Ph.D. Aaron J. Lorenz

Subject: Genomic selection on soybean NAM populations / Breeding for Asian Soybean Rust tolerance.

2018 – 2020 MBA in Business Management

University of São Paulo - USP/ESALQ

MBA thesis: Portfolio diversification and re-balancing: impacts on risk-return trade-off.

2016 – 2017 MBA in Project Management

University of São Paulo - USP/ESALQ

MBA thesis: Associations between global indices of risk management and agricultural development through multivariate analysis.

2013 - 2015 M.Sc. Agronomy

Federal University of Technology - UTFPR, Paraná, Brazil.

Advisor: Ph.D. Giovani Benin

Dissertation: Evaluation of genetic and environmental effects on yield improvements, baking quality and stability of wheat.

2008 – 2012 B.Sc. Agronomy

Federal University of Technology - UTFPR, Paraná, Brazil.

2005 – 2007 Agriculture and Livestock Technician

State Center for Professional Education in the Southwest of Paraná - CEEP-Sudoeste, Paraná, Brazil

Employment History

2020 - pres	Postdoctoral Researcher at Center for Quantitative Genetics and Genomics - QGG, Aarhus
	University, Denmark.
2017 - 2019	Doctorate Research Fellow São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP).
2016 - 2020	Master Business Administration Advisor at PECEGE Institute.

Visiting Scholar, University of Minnesota, Saint Paul Campus, Minnesota, USA.

2015 – 2017 **Doctorate Research Fellow** Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education Personnel (CAPES).

Employment History (continued)

- 2013 2015 Master's Degree Research Fellow Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education Personnel (CAPES).
 - 2012 **Research Intern** Tropical Melhoramento & Genética (TMG), Cambé PR.
- 2008 2012 Scientific Initiation Research Fellow National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq).

Peer-reviewed publications

Journal Articles

- Benin, G., Milioli, A. S., Meira, D., ..., **Bornhofen, E.** & ... (2020). UTF 25 Early bread wheat cultivar with white flour. *Crop Breeding and Applied Biotechnology*, 20. doi:10.1590/1984-70332020v20n4c67
- Espolador, F. G., Yassue, R. M., Marosini, J. S., **Bornhofen, E.**, Barbosa, P. A. M., Souza, R. S. e. & Vello, N. A. (2020). Assessing tolerance to Asian soybean rust in soybean inbred lines from exotic and adapted crosses. *Euphytica*, 216. doi:10.1007/s10681-020-02597-8
- Souza, R. S., Barbosa, P. A. M., Yassue, R. M., **Bornhofen, E.**, Espolador, F. G., Nazato, F. M. & Vello, N. A. (2020). Combining ability for the improvement of vegetable soybean. *Agronomy Journal*. doi:10.1002/agj2.20322
- **Bornhofen, E.**, Ramires, T. G., Bergonci, T., Nakamura, L. R. & Righetto, A. J. (2019). Associations between global indices of risk management and agricultural development. *Agricultural Systems*, 173, 281–288. doi:10.1016/j.agsy.2019.03.006
- Yassue, R. M., Bornhofen, E., Espolador, F. G., Barbosa, P. A. M., Souza, R. S. e. & Vello, N. A. (2019). Uni and multivariate approaches for diallel analysis in early generation trials for soybean tolerance to rust. *Bragantia*, 78, 522–534. doi:10.1590/1678-4499.20190037
- **Bornhofen, E.**, Todeschine, M., Stoco, M., Madureira, A., Marchioro, V. S., Storck, L. & Benin, G. (2018). Wheat Yield Improvements in Brazil: Roles of Genetics and Environment. *Crop Science*, 58(3), 1082–1093. doi:10.2135/cropsci2017.06.0358
- **Bornhofen, E.**, Woyann, L. G., Bozi, A. H., Stoco, M. G., Marchioro, V. S. & Benin, G. (2018). Associations between agronomic and bread-making quality traits in wheat: location and crop-year effects. *Científica*, 46(1), 38–41. doi:10.15361/1984-5529.2018v46n1p38-41
- Benin, G., Storck, L., Marchioro, V. S., **Bornhofen, E.**, Woyann, L. G. & Trevizan, D. M. T. (2017). Environment-specific selection to identify high yielding wheat genotypes and response to fungicide application. *Ceres*, 64(2), 167–175. doi:10.1590/0034-737X201764020009
- 9 Bornhofen, E., Benin, G., Storck, L., Marchioro, V. S., Meneguzzii, C., Miliolii, A. S. & Trevizani, D. M. (2017). Environmental effect on genetic gains and its impact on bread-making quality traits in Brazilian spring wheat. *Chilean journal of agricultural research*, 77(1), 27–34. doi:10.4067/S0718-58392017000100003
- Bornhofen, E., Benin, G., Storck, L., Woyann, L. G., Duarte, T., Stoco, M. G. & Marchioro, V. S. (2017). Statistical methods to study adaptability and stability of wheat genotypes. *Bragantia*, 76(1), 1–10. doi:10.1590/1678-4499.557
- Storck, L., Benin, G., Marchioro, V. S., Silva, R. R., Woyann, L. G. & **Bornhofen, E.** (2016). Strategy for grouping wheat genotypes according to environmental responses in multi-location trials. *Australian Journal of Crop Science*, 10(4), 571–578. doi:10.21475/ajcs.2016.10.04.p7450x
- Todeschini, M. H., Milioli, A. S., Trevizan, D. M., **Bornhofen, E.**, Finatto, T., Storck, L. & Benin, G. (2016). Nitrogen use efficiency in modern wheat cultivars. *Bragantia*, 75(3), 1–11. doi:10.1590/1678-4499.385

- Bornhofen, E., Benin, G., Galvan, D. & Flores, M. F. (2015). Épocas De Semeadura E Desempenho Qualitativo De Sementes De Soja. *Pesquisa Agropecuaria Tropical*, 45(1), 46–55. doi:10.1590/S0100-204X2012000100003
- Silva, C. L., Benin, G., Rosa, A. C., Beche, E., **Bornhofen, E.** & Capelin, M. A. (2015). Monitoring levels of deoxynivalenol in wheat flour of Brazilian varieties. *Chilean Journal of Agricultural Research*, 75(1), 50–56. doi:10.4067/S0718-583920150001200007
- Silva, C. L., **Bornhofen, E.**, Todeschini, M. H., Milioli, A. S., Trevizan, D. M. & Benin, G. (2015). Seleção de genótipos de trigo para rendimento de grãos e qualidade de panificação em ensaios multiambientes. *Ceres*, 62(4), 360–371. doi:10.1590/0034-737X201562040005
- Beche, E., Benin, G., **Bornhofen, E.**, Dalló, S. C., Sassi, L. H. & Oliveira, R. (2014). Eficiência de uso de nitrogênio em cultivares de trigo pioneiras e modernas. *Pesquisa Agropecuária Brasileira*, 49(12). doi:10.1590/S0100-204X2014001200005
- Lemes, C. S., Benin, G., **Bornhofen, E.**, Matheus, H. T., Dallo, S. C. & Scarparo, L. H. (2014). Characterization of brazilian wheat cultivars in terms of nitrogen use efficiency. *Bragantia*, 73(2), 1–10. doi:10.1590/brag.2014.012
- Silva, C. L., Benin, G., **Bornhofen, E.**, Beche, E., Todeschini, M. H. & Milioli, A. S. (2014). Nitrogen use efficiency is associated with chlorophyll content in Brazilian spring wheat. *Australian Journal of Crop Science*, 8(6), 957–964.
- Bornhofen, E., Benin, G., Matei, G., Silva, C. L., Beche, E., Pagliosa, E. S., ... Pinnow, C. (2013). Capacidade de combinação entre genitores de trigo em duas gerações Combining ability of wheat parents in two generations. *Semina: Ciências Agrárias*, 34(1), 3129–3140. doi:10.5433/1679-0359.2013v34n6Supl1p3129
- Viola, R., Benin, G., Cassol, L. C., Pinnow, C., Flores, M. F. & **Bornhofen, E.** (2013). Adubação verde e nitrogenada na cultura do trigo em plantio direto. *Bragantia*, 72(1), 90–100. doi:10.1590/S0006-87052013005000013
- Benin, G., Bornhofen, E., Beche, E., Pagliosa, E. S., Silva, C. L. & Pinnow, C. (2012). Agronomic performance of wheat cultivars in response to nitrogen fertilization levels. *Acta Scientiarum. Agronomy*, 34(3), 275–283. doi:10.4025/actasciagron.v34i3.14468
- Benin, G., Pinnow, C., da Silva, C. L., Pagliosa, E. S., Beche, E., Bornhofen, E., ... Silva, R. R. (2012). Análises biplot na avaliação de cultivares de trigo em diferentes níveis de manejo. *Bragantia*, 71(1), 28–36. doi:10.1590/S0006-87052012000100005

Conference Proceedings (4 out of 49)

- Bornhofen, E. & Vello, N. A. (2019). Tolerance to rust-induced stress: A comprehensive study on the benefits and constraints to soybean breeding. In *Proceedings of the crops2019 conference*, Huntsville, Alabama, USA. Shttp://goo.gl/pfdUfm
- Bornhofen, E., Lorenz, A. & Vello, N. A. (2018). Unraveling the potential use of tolerance as a defense strategy against asian soybean rust. In *Proceedings of the 17th biennial conference on the molecular and cellular biology of the soybean*, Athens, Georgia, USA. & http://goo.gl/pfdUfm
- Bornhofen, E., Vello, N. A., Espolador, F. G., Yassue, R. M. & Nekatschalow, M. C. (2017). Assessing soybean rust tolerance and the impacts on seed traits. In *Proceedings of the 9th brazilian plant breeding congress*, Foz do Iguacu, Paraná, BR. & https://goo.gl/hwrfY2
- Bornhofen, E., Vello, N. A., Espolador, F. G., Yassue, R. M. & Souza, R. S. (2017). Exploring soybean traits through multivariate analysis in contrasting rust environments. In *Proceedings of the 2nd latin-american conference on plant phenotyping and phenomics for plant breeding*, São Carlos, São Paulo, BR. & https://goo.gl/2fy3va

Books and Chapters

1

Vegetable Soybean. (2017). Piracicaba, São Paulo, Brazil: Library and documentation division, University of São Paulo, ESALQ/USP. % https://goo.gl/iFi5VK

Intellectual property

Crop variety UTF 25 - Protected wheat cultivar [MAPA process: 21806.000111/2019] developed at the

Federal University of Technology - Paraná | shorturl.at/ilQ17.

Skills

Portuguese:

Languages English:

Spanish:

Coding R, LATEX, Python, Bash, Markdown.

Softwares ASreml, Atom, DMU package, Microsoft 365 products, Photoshop, RStudio, Wordpress.

Misc. Academic research, teaching, training, consultation, statistical learning, project management, business management, solid interpersonal skills, and strong creative thinking (analytical,

problem-solving, open-minded, and organization).

Miscellaneous Experience

Awards and Achievements

2018 **Certification of Achievement (second prize)**, Graduate student poster competition, presented at the 17th Biennial Conference on the Molecular and Cellular Biology of the Soybean, August 26-29th, Athens, Georgia, USA.

Research Internship Abroad (BEPE - FAPESP) process number 2017/24266-0.

- 2017 **Doctorate Fellowship FAPESP** process number 2017/11235-0.
- Approved in the first position for the Ph.D. program in Genetics and Plant Breeding, ESALQ/USP, 2015/2.
- Approved for the position of extensionist at EMATER-PR, process number 148/2014, resolution number 13274.

Leadership & Membership

2019 – pres Brazilian Society of Plant Breeding.

2017 – 2019 Gvenck Member, Genetics and Plant Breeding Group "Prof. Roland Vencovsky" (Gvenck).

2014 – 2015 Graduate Students Representative at Federal University of Technology, Graduate Program in Agronomy.

Courses (3 out of 18)

2017 Introduction to Bayesian Inference (16h), Department of Statistics, University of São Paulo, ESAL/USP, Piracicaba, São Paulo.

2016 **Mixed models and variance components (120h)**, Department of Statistics, University of São Paulo, ESALQ/USP, Piracicaba, São Paulo.

2013 **Techniques for a better public speaking (21h)**, National Service for Commercial Training - Senac, Pato Branco, Paraná.

International Events (8 out of 13)

2019 Brazilian Congress of Plant Breeding, Águas de Lindóia, São Paulo, BRA.

Miscellaneous Experience (continued)

CROPS2019: Improving agriculture through genomics, Huntsville, Alabama, USA.

2018 **2nd International Meeting on Plant Breeding (organizing committee)**, Piracicaba, São Paulo, BRA.

SOY2018 Conference: 17th Biennial Conference on the Molecular and Cellular Biology of the Soybean, Athens, Georgia, USA.

New Frontiers in Genetic Evaluation, Dupont/Pioneer headquarters, Johnston, Iowa, USA.

University of Minnesota Plant Sciences Symposium - From markers to markets, Saint Paul, Minnesota, USA.

2017 Second Latin-American Conference on Plant Phenotyping and Phenomics for Plant Breeding, Embrapa Instrumentation, São Carlos, São Paulo, BRA.

9th Brazilian Congress of Plant Breeding, Foz do Iguaçu, Paraná, BRA.

References

Available upon request.